My light's on.
Good evening everyone.
6 o'lock on the button, so I'll call to
order this July 1st uh meeting of
Lancaster City Council committees. Uh
Mr. Harris, would you please call the
role of members this evening? Yes, Madam
President. Mr. Matt, Mr. Royo here, Mr.
Cle here, Miss Craig, Miss Diaz here,
Mr. Hirs here, and President Baker here,
councilors Amed and Craig are excused
this evening. A few reminders for
everyone. Um, at the top of the meeting,
I ask that you please silence your
phones and devices if you haven't done
so already. Please know that this
meeting and its participants are being
recorded. Tonight we have meetings of
committees of council. There are no
general public comment periods during
this meeting. However, committee chairs
will call for comments from the public
on legislative items which are bills and
resolutions. Comments are limited to
three minutes per speaker and must begin
with your name and block of residence
for the meeting record.
Right, counselors. Um first of all, if
there's an issue with the mic, we can
switch it out with another one that's
over there. Don't think uh Okay. Um
mayor, would you switch one? Yes. Thank
you.
Thank you for bearing with us through
technical difficulties.
Yeah. Perfect. Uh councilors, we'll
begin before the committees with the
approval of the June 2nd, 2025 committee
meeting minutes.
Motion to approve. Second. I have a
motion and a second. Any council
discussion on the minutes?
Right. Mr. Harris, would you call the
vote on that?
Mr. Roya. I. Mr. Please I, Miss Diaz.
I, Mr. Hirs. I, President B. I. Thank
you. All right. We begin tonight with
the personnel committee. Councelor Kix.
Thank you, Madame President. The
personnel committee has uh four items on
the agenda for tonight. And all four
items are nominations to for
reappointment to the uh fire code board
appeals. And the nominees are Dennis
Park, Kenneth Barton, Lloyd Henry, and
Jin Duncan. And uh they currently serve
on the board, and they have expressed
that their willingness to be
reappointed. I'll open up for questions
or comments from other member of the
committees and council.
Councelor Cle, just to make a note that
for reappoints, we typically don't ask
the the folks to come before council. Is
that correct? Yes, correct. Thank you.
And thank you to them for serving.
Any comments or questions from the
public?
Hearing none. So, I'll make a motion to
move those nominations to our next
council meeting. Second. All in favors?
I. I. Madame President, that concludes
the personal committee. Thank you very
much, Councelor Klest. We'll now move to
the finance committee. Uh, councelor
Royo.
Thank you, Council President. Uh, we
have three items on the agenda for this
evening. First is administration
resolution number 48 2025, which is
authorizing the disposal of public works
vehicles. Um, and I believe uh, sorry,
Director Campbell is here to speak on
that resolution.
Good evening.
Good evening, council.
Good evening, Dr. Campbell. Good
evening. Good evening.
So, we're very pleased to be able to
bring this presentation to you. It's
partly asking for the the disposition of
these vehicles through auction, but also
to give you a little bit of an update of
the status of the vehicle of the fleet
vehicle program.
So, next slide, please.
The resolution is asking to authorize
the disposal and acquisition of vehicles
for DPW.
The resolution overview is such that
we're disposing of vehicles by auction.
We want to dispose of six vehicles as
per the on the list of ex by exhibit A
um that are no longer planned to be of
service. The trade in of vehicles of 14
vehicles for other for other vehicles to
be acquired by sale or lease and 11
vehicles to be rolled into new leases at
best price. The estimated value the
council estimates that the value of
vehicles to be sold to be in excess of
$2,000 each.
and the authorization to proper official
of to profer officials of the city of
Lancaster authorized to sell and trade
in the vehicles. Officials are also
authorized to take necessary actions to
accomplish the purpose of the
resolution.
Next slide.
Thank you. Um the progress just as an
update the progress of the fleet
management program is is as follows. We
have as you know entered into a contract
with enterprise fleet management which
tracks equity in each vehicle and
recommends replacement when our equity
is at highest. So it's it's a best
management practice.
the uh we have been able so far in the
approximately 14 to 16 months that the
contract has been in place to reduce the
fleet from 251 to 239 vehicles or reduce
it by 12 vehicles.
It all it gives us the opportunity to
look at a fleet sharing model which we
have implemented in part here at city
hall for and it allows us opportunities
for further reductions based on usage.
At this moment, we have approximately
uh 12 vehicles that are in full-time use
and an an additional four four vehicles
that are not in full-time use. We
believe that we can reduce the fleet
share by that four, but we're waiting
for a little bit more data to confirm um
what this what the enterprise fleet
management program allows us to do is to
monitor usage as well as where the
vehicle goes, how fast it's being used,
if is it violating traffic laws, things
like that.
It also this program may also allow us
further reduction in police bureau
vehicles as possible.
Next,
some of the other metrics of the fleet
management program. We have saved 81,000
in in with the enterp enterprise fleet
management of ordering of 27 vehicles
and maintenance in the first year. So
most of these are are statistics of the
first 12 months of the of the contract.
Um first year of the program 154
services recorded with in-house auto
integrate program which is the program
that monitors the the condition. It's
kind of like the the uh equipment the
equip equipment flag on your vehicle. It
lets us know when there's something
going wrong that needs to be attended
to. Uh, it allowed for the resale. We
sold 57 city-owned vehicles with
$362,000
worth of equity slashtradein value
rolled into the new leases. Now, that
sound that may sound like it's just a
direct savings, but basically it allows
us to leverage the funds and the value,
the equity in the bu in the in the
vehicles to acquire better better
performing vehicles, stronger vehicles.
um more modern vehicles where it's
appropriate. We don't go for modern just
for the sake of being modern. We go for
modern only if it is if it is in our
best interest.
Um
we it also in terms of resale it we
leased the least unit generated $15,000.
One leased unit generated $15,000 and
was sold at 8% above the industry. Uh
meaning a 300 3,152
back to the city or approximately a uh
20% uh um benefit. That is that is one
of the metrics that we're looking to
continually repeat. It allows us to to
look at each of the vehicles in that
kind of a context.
philanthropy partnerships. The Lancaster
City Police Foundation received two
$2,500 grant from Enterprise Foundation
and the much many of the metrics above
contribute to the cost per unit
decreasing by a little bit more than 20%
down to 44 cents per mile versus
approximately 56 cents per mile just
last year.
next.
Okay. Um the the again we don't have
metrics. We have uh apoc.
Okay. Thank you for bearing with us. I
know we're work we're work we're we're
still exploring these. It might be that.
Let's try that. That's okay. We'll
figure it out once and once we get it,
it'll be fantastic. Exactly. Then we
will get a whole new system once we
figure it out. It works. It works.
So, um, again, we we have only anecdotal
information from years previous to 2024,
2024, but the average miles per gallon
for the current vehicles in our fleet is
approximately 25 m miles per gallon. Um
the approximately the vehicle age has
decreased in the in this last year alone
from 6.5 years to 5.7 years.
Meaning that by by being able to
leverage the the vehicles at their prime
we have better younger vehicles.
The fleet value of the 250 vehicles
monitored by enterprise is approximately
$4.3 million.
And the Geotab telematics enrollment
which is part of the technology that
tracks this information is the for the
250 vehicles tracks location of the
vehicles. So we know where the vehicles
are 247 365
uh speed aggressive driving etc. This is
very important as we monitor and try to
determine what appropriate policies for
enforcement as well as for utiliz
utilization of the vehicles is. And it
also contributes to our increased
intention to have more fleet share
rather than fleet uh specific fleet for
um for city uses.
Next and last slide.
So just a quick summary of the auction
and tradein details. We're looking at
auctioning six vehicles to be sold via
the via gov deals which is the means by
which we can work with the local auction
houses whenever the vehicles are appro
are available and get the best price.
Trade in of 14 vehicles to be traded for
new acquisitions. 11 vehicles to be
rolled into new leases and the
replacement process uh in terms of
explanation of timelines and next steps
auction as replacement vehicles arrive.
So we would not be eliminating vehicles
before we have the replacement. Um and
the auctions are perpetual. They they
they're not just once or twice a year.
They're often every weekend. The old
units get decommissioned and readied for
readied for sale. uh which allows us to
again maximize the price that they can
be sold at and auctions are ongoing
online and enterprise sales via the auto
auto auctions. So the request again is
to be able to to
um auction those six vehicles and to be
able to trade in the 14 vehicles for new
acquisitions as well as 11 vehicles to
be rolled into new leases.
Great. Thank you, Director Campbell. Um,
I don't have any questions or comments.
Are there any questions or comments from
the committee or full counsel? Councelor
Diaz, if I may, um, regarding the cars,
what make models are there? Um, there's
a there is a uh an exhibit A which has a
list of each of the vehicles. I'm not
sure if you guys have that. It should
have been with the
We do. Yeah. So the the six to be
auctioned are at the top. There's
another grouping of 14 which are the
ones for the trading for new
acquisitions. They're make, model, and
year. And then the 11 vehicles to be
rolled into new leases are the the
following 11 group of 11.
Were you able to find it? For some
reason, it's not downloading for me, but
I'll I'll look for it.
Thank you.
Um, I do have a hard council president.
Thank you. Um, as you're looking for
that, Director Campbell, I'm I'm looking
at the exhibit A and I just So
maybe maybe I just need to kind of
conceptualize we're talking about fleet
management because some of the vehicles
in the first list are things like dump
trucks and sweepers and gators and so is
enterprise fleet management also
managing our fleet of those sort of
specialty vehicles as well? It's a very
good question. They are not managing
that fleet. However, they are the ones
who would be selling at auction any of
those fleet that we do have. Understood.
Under that category. Thank you for that
clarification.
Any add?
Thank you, councelor Jimmy. Councelor,
how are you? Thank you. And uh D
Campbell, what is the process for
determining a public switch vehicle is
ready for disposal?
Um what what we have it's a very good
question. And what we have done is the
contract for enterprise allows us to
have assessed basically done a facility
assessment of the condition of all the
vehicles that they are managing. The 250
vehicles that they are managing by age,
by condition, by
a crash history, um by a variety of
other things that that may determine
what its value is. and then compare that
via um a variety of other metrics with
what the market will bear. So it we're
looking at what can our vehicles in our
particular situation,
what are they worth, what equity might
they might acrue to them in order for us
to determine whether we sell them or
not. I'm sorry touching this thing. Um
uh in order to sell them at at an
appropriate level or not. If for
instance a vehicle is older but still I
think it just might be the speaker.
If it is older but in a in a in still
good shape um that would allow us to
there's there's kind of a calculus that
would indicate whether it's at its at
its optimum for equity
for for selling to get the benefit of
its equity or not. Um similarly, if it's
a younger vehicle, but it has been in a
crash and has had uh been plagued by
lemon issues by
uh problems with with the vehicle that
would indicate that it would be ready to
be sold earlier than later
and uh who is involved in that decision?
It's primarily enterprise. They are an
industry leader in this kind of work.
And we have when we did the when we did
the competitive uh um solicitation, we
were looking at several different firms
on a national level and they came in
giving us the best metrics with a
dashboard that we we are able to use and
have access to the data on a vehicle-by-
vehicle basis daily at any way that we
like. So we got the best what we what we
believe is the best value for the
proposal in that competitive proposing
period.
Thank you, Daryl. Thank you, councelor.
How are you? Yeah. Thank you. Any
additional questions or comments from
council?
Great. Any questions from the public?
Yes, I do. Thank you.
Tony Dastro, 700 block New Holland
Avenue. I I just really need to express
the frustration at the audio for a
moment
because I'm sitting there and I
understand I'm not frustrated at any
individual here. I know it's tough to
work through, but it's not a laughing
matter.
these sort of issues if they carry
through to the live stream are the
difference between someone tuning in to
engage themselves civically and educate
themselves
and not so I just need to say that
and leave it there. Um
the only question I have is I mean we've
already made changes to certain other
uh processes in the city regarding the
sale of property. Um, has there been any
investigation as to whether these
vehicles could be used for local
nonprofit needs? Because while I respect
getting the highest dollar value for
these things, sometimes the greatest
return comes from empowering our
community organizations.
Um, thank you for that question. We did
not look at alternate uses of the
vehicles. Uh, partly because many of
them are very unique vehicles. They're
for specific uses or specific have
specific characteristics and that would
mitigate our ability to to uh
financially benefit from them. It does
not m it does not reduce the value that
they might have had for other purposes,
but it does increase the amount of
effort and the overhead to be able to
manage the disposition of those vehicles
in a non-competitive setting. We would
be looking at several different types of
solicitation to be able to make those
available uh as well as um the hands-on
efforts of of managing such transfers.
Great. Thank you, Director Campbell.
With that, um I will motion to move
admin uh resolution number 48 2025 to
full counsel.
All those in favor? I
move on to Thank you, Director Campbell.
Councelor Royal. Yes, council. Can I
just make a note? I want to just ensure
council and members of the public in the
room that um we have been told that the
live stream is not affected by the
popping noises that we're hearing. It's
coming in through the speaker in the
room and so the audio feed is coming in
separately through streaming.
Thank you. Thank you, Council President.
Next item on the agenda is resolution
number 492025 which is authorizing a
funding project uh for uh it's listed on
the agenda as Lancaster Industrial
Development Authority on behalf of
Lutherare. Um it is actually the
Lancaster Mun Municipal Authority um on
behalf of Lutherare. Um and we have
representatives from the municipal
authority here. Great. We have Oh, thank
you.
Let me come on up.
Good even good evening. Is this on? Yes.
Yes. Okay. My name is Aaron Hollis. I am
solicitor for Langster Municipal
Authority and we are requesting approval
for a taxexempt financing for Luther
Care. Uh it's for $26 million for
acquisition and development of 37 new
homes and their property in Litz as well
as other capital improvements. This is
uh conduit financing. Uh this is not an
obligation of the city. This would be
coming from a a lender. Langster
municipal authorities name will be on it
but will not have direct obligation on
these um the notes for this. Uh this is
a project in lit. We are also seeking
approval in Litz Burough, Warwick
Township and Columbia Burough. Lure
Municipal Authority was approved under
the city and we also under the code
require approval from Laner City. have
we also have a representative of
Lutherare if you have any questions
about the project. Right. Thank you. Um
similar resolution came before council
maybe a year ago um or as far as um on
behalf of the Langster Municipal
Authority and as I think one of the
biggest questions was uh does this uh
obligate the city to any um financial
obligation and it doesn't. It does not.
No, it it has no direct obligation to
the city and even Langster Municipal
Authority has no direct obligation for
this. It is through the documents. It is
a note issue through Lan Municipal
Authority but has no direct obligation.
Great. Thank you. Um I'll open up the
for or open up for any questions or
comments from the committee
or full counsel.
Right. Any questions from the public?
Thank you. Thank you. Yeah. With that, I
will motion to move resolution number
49, 2022 to full counsel.
Motion in a second. All those in favor?
I.
Great. Uh, next on the agenda for the
finance committee, we have a report on
the earned income tax exemption. Um,
I'll invite Director Campbell to the
table.
Good evening, Director Campbell. Good
evening.
Um, thank you for uh requesting this. I
think councelor Hirs requested this um
report this evening. Um I'm going to
provide some information regarding a
possible earned income tax exemption for
lower income residents. Um, and we have
put together a few considerations um,
for you as well as some some data to
show you. I'm pausing until he gets the
presentation up here. So, be before we
start, I would like to add just a small
caveat. Um, we've done quite a bit of
research on this. Um, I hope you'll see
that through some of these
considerations. Um, however, I do want
to say we haven't taken a thorough dive
into any of the particular
considerations. Um, so the presentation
tonight is estimates from what we've
learned. These estimates will not be
exact and they will require further work
depending on how council decides to
pursue next steps. Um, we'll move into
further considerations for the options
based on on your um on your proposals.
We tried to balance staff time for the
purpose of the initial report knowing
that um this is the first step in the
process.
All right, next slide.
Um, so tonight's agenda, it's a it's
short sections, so this isn't going to
be a a long uh report, but there's five
different short sections. Um, we'll give
a quick overview of earned income tax,
review some of the data um from that.
We'll bring some considerations forward
for you to think about as you're making
decisions on on um how to move forward.
We'll look at some financial estimates.
Um we'll have some potential
alternatives in here as well and then
we'll talk about next steps.
Next slide please. Um so before we dive
into the exemption, we thought we would
give a review of what the earned income
tax actually is. We've been talking
about this quite a bit during the home
rule um process. So, the earned income
tax or EIT um you'll see it referred to
as EIT up here. It's a tax paid on
income earned um by anyone who lives in
the city. So, the current rate paid by
city residents is 1.1% of their income.
Um generally the state maximum
percentage is 6% but the home rule
charter allows municipalities to go
higher than that. Um and so the 1.1 was
voted on with the budget um as of
January 1st because of the home roll
charter. Um this is the city's portion
of the earned income tax. The school
district also collects an earned income
tax and they currently collect 0.5%. So
the total earned income tax that the
city residents pay is 1.6%.
Uh earned income tax is only paid on
income earned. So it's not paid on
social security income. So that means
that many retired individuals would not
be paying the earned income tax.
Next slide please.
All right. So an earned income tax
exemption um this can be determined for
income earners making less than a
certain amount. The state sets the
maximum income earned for the exemption
at $12,000.
and we believe that this is the ceiling
regardless of home status uh for any
municipality in Pennsylvania.
We currently don't have an exemption for
the earned income tax and this is what
we're going to explore a little bit this
evening. I will just note there's
another tax, the local service tax. Um
this is collected from anyone who works
in the city regardless of where they
live. We do offer an exemption for that
tax. um the if the income is under
12,000 and again that's the state
maximum.
Next slide please.
So um we want to give a few data points
for you from across the state. Um so
from what we found there's currently we
think 36 municipalities in Pennsylvania
that are currently offering an earned
income tax exemption. This is uh
actually 1.4% of all municipalities in
Pennsylvania. So there's about 2600
municipalities across the state.
This is according to the DCED website
and uh we discovered that this number
might actually still be a little high.
Uh one of the municipalities shown to be
giving an earned in income tax exemption
is in Lancaster County. So we actually
reached out to them and they did they
were not aware that they were offering
this exemption. So um so that but this
is what the DCD uh list is showing at
this time.
So, of the 36 municipalities, 11 of them
have a population over 10,000. And
there's one Ben Ben Salem, which is
close to Philadelphia, um that's
slightly larger than Lancaster City, uh
with a population just over 60,000. All
of the other um municipalities are
smaller than Lancaster. So, we would be
one of the largest um to have this
exemption.
Um about twothirds of the municipalities
have a population under 10,000. Um the
smallest municipality offering this uh
is uh made up of 422 people. So it's
quite small. Um and none of the 36
municipalities have an exemption that's
above 12,000. Um they actually range
anywhere from 200 up to 12,000. Um which
was interesting to see.
All right, next slide please.
Um so some considerations to think
about. Um,
as we were reviewing this, um, our
solicitor, Mr. Hanburgger, uh, reviewed
some of the exemption level requirements
and as I mentioned, um, we were
conferring with some outside consultants
as well, and they believe that we cannot
go above that $12,000 income level, um,
regardless of the home rule status, as I
stated earlier. So, I'm focusing data
tonight on what it would look like for
Lancaster to do this at the $12,000
level.
Um, additionally, we met with the
Lancaster County Tax Collection Bureau.
Um, and they actually provided quite a
bit of data for us uh to look into,
which was really helpful for this
process. Um, so they uh also uh went out
and talked to a second tax collection a
agency that works with the large portion
of the 36 municipalities who are
currently doing the exemptions. And
these are some considerations that come
from both the Lancaster uh county tax
collection bureau as well as this other
tax collection bureau. Um one of them is
that we would want to ensure that
there's some provision that this would
only be eligible for anyone who has
lived in the city for the full calendar
year. Otherwise, someone who has a
higher income might move into the city
very late in the year but still receive
the exemption because of that income
threshold.
Um the exemption must work on a refund
basis. This is required for two reasons.
Um one is we're not able to determine
who is making less than the threshold
until after taxes are filed. Um so
residents would still need to pay the
tax throughout the year and then be
refunded um after they file the tax. Um
the second's actually more important. Um
because the school district receives a
portion of the tax and that portion is
not exempt, they would still need to pay
that portion. So the tax is collected at
the full percentage and then divided
between the city and the school
district. So it can't be withheld
throughout the year.
Um residents would need to file the
taxes by the tax deadline in order to
have the tax collection bureau have
capacity to process the refunds. And I
I'm going to mention a bit later that
the tax collection bureau would be the
ones processing these these refunds. Um
the the bureau estimates that only about
50% of residents actually file taxes um
timely at this point. Um that said, if
and if there is an exemption as an
option, we would anticipate that more
tax payers would be filing in a more
timely manner.
Um, and then finally, in discussion with
the tax collection bureau, we've also
determined um that really the only
reasonable option to have these
exceptions processed would be to have
them do do the do the processing for us.
Um, as we talked about it, because of
some of the confidential taxpayer
information, it'd be very difficult to
get the information needed to city staff
or other issu or other entities to
actually issue the refunds. Um, but they
have agreed uh that they could do the
work for a fee. So that was that was a
helpful step to determine.
All right, next slide please.
Okay, so some of the numbers this is
where it may get a little complicated.
So I'm going to try to keep this as try
to explain it as best I can. Um so these
numbers are estimates using 2024
numbers. Um we had to make some educated
assumptions. As I mentioned earlier, we
don't have historic trends to show us um
you know this type of exemption shift at
this point. Um so we're using some um
some estimations here. Uh based on the
2024 percentage of tax filers, um the
city would receive approximately
130,000
uh in income from about 3600 taxpayers
making 12,000 or less annually. This is
if if um taxpayers were filing at the at
the rate that they are typically filing
now.
We're estimating that approximately 20%
uh more taxpayers would file with the
incentive of a refund. So that would
equal about 258,000
uh with a total of about 4,600
individual taxpayers.
So the dollar amount, as you can see,
almost doubles um from the 130,000 to
the 258,000.
um with this additional filing um and
that's because the the taxpayers earning
closer to 12,000 would likely be the
ones to file at a greater number or this
is what we're anticipating. So we would
anticipate that there would be higher
amounts um coming in for that and
therefore for the purposes of this
estimate we're using that 258,000.
We're considering that 258,000 to be
kind of the lost revenue for the city.
Um, I'm putting that in quotes, but that
would be technically uh what would no
longer be available as tax revenue.
So, this is where it it may get a little
complicated, but of this 258,000, we now
need to consider um a non-resident
earned income tax. Um
the nonresident earned income tax
applies to anyone living in the city but
working in a a different municipality.
So residents are charged one earned
income tax. I mentioned that it's
together the city and the school
district. Um this earned income tax will
first go to the m municipality in which
they live. If the municipality that the
resident lives in decides not to charge
an earned income tax or if it's
refunded, um the municipality that
they're working in has a right to
collect a non-resident tax. So we we
actually collect a non-resident earned
income tax from this as well. And I'll
give you just it's it's very a very
small amount. In June, our total earned
income tax that came in was 526,000.
Non-residentident of that, the
non-resident portion was 5,000. So it's
about 1%.
So back to this example, if someone
lives in the city but works in Mannheim
Township, Mannheim Township would
generally not collect the non-resident
tax because the city gets the tax first
before the outside municipality would.
However, if the resident living in
Lancaster City gets an exemption to that
1.1% rate, in essence, this means that
the resident has not yet paid an earned
income tax. So then Mannheim Township
would be eligible to receive their
non-resident tax at their rate, which at
this point is 6%.
Because they don't have that exemption,
they would receive that funding and then
the resident would receive a refund of
0.5% instead of the full 1.1%.
So based on what the tax collection
bureau could obtain in the last couple
of weeks, looking at you know uh
residents living in the city um and
working outside, it looks like
approximately 117,000 of the 258,000
would be paid to other municipalities.
The taxpayer would then receive about
141,000 as a refund and the average
refund would be about $42 per resident.
Um, and then additionally, we would we
would uh be paying a fee to the tax
collection bureau for the work. Um, it
would be about $10 per filing. So about
$47,000 we're figuring. So the city's
total outlay um with the revenue
reduction and the expenses for
processing would be approximately
304,000.
And 141,000 of that, so about 46% less
than half of the total outlay would
actually go back to the taxpayers.
Um, that's a lot of numbers. So, the
next slide's going to just graph it out
a little bit for us.
Um, this is showing uh on the left hand
side what would go to the other
municipalities, the processing fee, and
then the refund to residents. And so,
you can kind of see regardless of what
what level the numbers are, you can kind
of see the percentages there a little
bit better as well.
All right, next slide.
Um, I want to give some potential
alternatives to this. Um, ultimately
council needs to decide about pursuing
an exemption. Um, however, given that
potentially more than half of the total
financial outlay may not actually end up
going back to the taxpayers, we wanted
to offer some other options. Um, so one
to consider would be an application
process. Um, this wouldn't necessarily
eliminate the um the the pieces that are
not going to the taxpayers, but it could
lower um the the processing u because
there might not be quite as many um
applications that would be coming
through. Um this piece we haven't
researched fully yet again so that we
would need some further consideration if
we would want to go that route.
Um we could also consider allocating um
you know basically the same portion um
that would have been refunded or would
have uh been our our total outlay to a
program that we might already be doing
um that that could be helping low-income
individuals. So a couple of them are
listed here. The critical repair fund uh
we've talked about that often at council
that specifically supports low-income
individuals in the city. Um, and it
would mean that all of the funds would
actually be kept to be used for city
residents. Um, we could also consider
allocating some uh to the Lancaster
water assistance program. Um, that's the
program that is offered through CAP for
um utility support for lower income
households. And we could designate uh
this is for um all of the households
that the the program is set up for all
of the households that uh we serve with
our utilities, but we could designate
this portion just for incity residents.
Um and then we could explore new
programs if you would like to help um
lower income households. Um we could
research next steps on those as well.
The last slide.
Um, so ultimately we'll need direction
from council on what you'd like to have
more information on. Um, as I mentioned,
these are all estimates at this point.
So once we have a general direction, we
can work on more concrete information to
provide. Um, and once the focus or
direction is determined, we um will
account for those costs in the budget.
Um, you know, we're currently working on
the budget. We'll have a final draft
hopefully completed by the last week in
September. Um, so we'd want to at least
include some estimates based on the
approach by then.
Thank you, Director Campbell. Uh, very
informative and I appreciate all the
hard work in doing the research to
answer this question. I know this is
something that's uh come up before
council and a lot of counselors interest
over the last few months since uh the
passing of the new home rule charter.
So, I appreciate providing some of this
clarity. Um, I know for me personally,
the the need to consider the
non-resident uh earned income tax was uh
relatively new information. That's
something that I was not aware of that
would uh get unlocked, for lack of a
better term, if we were to provide an
exemption on the earned income tax. Um,
it's also pretty startling to think that
it would actually cost us more money uh
to provide the exemption than would
actually be collected. So, if am I right
in thinking in noting the $258,000 that
would have been collected um and then
refunded as a as a exemption would
actually cost the city in total 304,000.
Correct. Yeah. Right. Yeah. Um so
definitely something to consider. Um I
do appreciate the alternatives as well.
I think um when we look at the problem
that we're trying to solve with the
exemption, it was providing relief to
low-income uh taxpayers here in the city
of Lancaster. uh and thinking about
other potential allocations to other
funds or other programs that offer that
direct impact. Um I know I'll speak for
myself, sounds a lot more appealing
knowing that uh the residents that need
it the most will receive um the full
dollar um of that impact um right here
in the city of Lancaster rather than a
portion. So um just some of my thoughts,
but happy to open up to the committee or
full counsel.
Um, thank you very much, Director
Campbell, for the thorough research. And
part of the reason I had asked for this
report is just knowing that it wasn't
just as simple as, you know, okay,
what's the budgetary impact if we say,
um, you know, on this increment of tax,
you don't have to pay tax. That there is
a lot of logistical considerations into
doing an exemption. and having heard a
lot of the logistical considerations,
um,
you've given us a lot to think about,
that's for sure. Um, and I don't want to
say I'm closing the door, but it
definitely sounds like kind of a lot of
headache for not necessarily a lot of
return. And, um,
I'm definitely I've grown a little
colder to this idea than maybe I came in
um, to this meeting. That said, you
know, I agree, councelor Royo. I think
any ways that we can return
uh
return tax dollars to low-income
residents um and to residents period
overall, I think is something that we
should always be looking into. Um you
know, and I'll just go back I'll finish
my comments just by saying, you know, I
really appreciated the presentation we
just got on the fleet management. Um,
you know, that's kind of I think an
example of like where we can return a
lot of value to taxpayers or at least it
it really I think show uh had shown
itself um in that presentation. Um so I
really admire the work that the city has
done with that. Um so like I said I I
will have to think about all of this. um
me personally um
you've given a lot lot given us a lot to
think about. So thank you very much
again for the thorough research and um
all the great information you were able
to gather.
Thank you councelor Hirs. Um any other
questions or comments from council
members? Councelor Royo. Council
president. Thank you. Thank you for the
presentation and I know it was a lot of
work to put together and I know that
further exploration will require a lot
more. Um, I appreciate I I want to echo
the sentiments that I think the giving
funds to other municipalities aspect of
this was eye openening uh and not
something that I'm particularly
interested in doing um as a steward of
the tax dollars uh the city of
Lancaster. Um but I do appreciate the
alternatives that are presented and I
think that we can this is people often
talk about getting creative and this is
one way where we could do that and so
this is a start and there may be some
other ideas. Um, speaking as your
council president, I'm very open to hear
those from counselors if you have other
thoughts whether they're on the list of
what's here or other ideas on how we can
make a better investment uh for our
lowest income residents. Um, just and
out of curiosity, I'm trying to do the
math and it's not necessarily my
strongest suit, but a person who makes
$11,999,
how much is that really at the current
tax rate?
is that they're paying like could
someone do that? It's like $142.
Yeah. Okay. And so they may get half of
that back in the end instead of the full
amount if we go through this process for
a full year. For a full year. Okay.
Thank you. I appreciate the com
appreciate confirming my math. Thank
you. If they don't live and work in the
If they live and work in the city, they
would get more back. But if they'd live
outside the city, it could be as little
as half. 46%. 46%. Thank you.
Great.
Any additional questions or comments
from council?
Great. Uh well, we have a lot to process
and to think about, but appreciate the
report, Director Campbell. Thank you,
Council.
Uh there's no action being taken on
this. So, since it's just a report from
council, there will be no public
comment.
With that, I'll close the uh finance
committee. Council President. Thank you,
Council Royo. I'm actually going to turn
it right back to you. Our next committee
is community planning. Council Craig is
absent this evening. So, council Royo,
if you would chair this one this
evening. Thank you, Council President.
Uh there are two items on the community
planning committee this evening. Uh the
first admin first is administration
resolution number 502025
which is authorizing a ground lease
agreement for uh Sunnyside environmental
center and I believe we have
Mr. Handworkers here.
There you go. Yeah. Good evening. I
figured I figured if we sent you 100
pages of legal documents, I probably
should
Well, I I appreciate that. I sent you
100 pages of legal documents and I
appreciated the executive summary as
well. So, thank you. So, as you recall,
uh it should be on with the red light
there. So, good. Uh as you recall,
you've already actually essentially
approved this in a previous resolution.
Um but uh given the fact that this is a
99-year lease, given the fact that uh
this is going to have impact on
generations of Lancaster residents uh
hereafter, u it's it's it's important
for city council to have the documents
and approve them before signature. Um
the executive summary I sent you the
summary uh prepared um essentially
covers the primary points of the
transaction the documents which are um
an agreement to enter into ground lease
and then subsequently ground lease. And
the reason they're broken out into two
parts is there's a there's a lengthy due
process
uh process, for lack of a better word,
that that Partners from Environmental
Stewardship will need to go through uh
in designing a building uh that will
meet the worldass standards that they've
committed to uh that will provide the
programming and impetus for um residents
of the city of Lancaster that will be in
conjunction with the with the preserve.
that's going to take at least 18 months
if not longer just to do some basic
design and research and then they've got
to go through land development process.
Um it is a lengthy process. Um there
hasn't been any testing done on the land
yet. So all of those things have to
happen which are fairly normal in a land
development transaction when somebody
buys land. The unique nature of this
transaction is that we are dividing
title right. So title as you get it when
you buy a house you get what's called
fee simple title. you own 100% of all
the interest in that property subject to
any rights that say a utility might have
for running electric. That would be an
easement. The difference here is that
we're not giving that interest to PES.
Rather, we're giving them a 99-year
ground lease. So essentially, we're
leasing the land to them and they get
that land to do to control build on as
set forth in these documents. And at the
end of the 99-year lease, it terminates
unless it's extended by the parties. U
so that's somewhat different type of
transaction than what we would normally
doing where you sell a house, buy a
house, or donate the house. Uh the
rationale for that is that was part of
the original transaction. It was so the
city is continuing to maintain its asset
which is the a little over eight acres,
almost nine acres that um the
environmental center will sit on and be
utilized. Um
once the due diligence is done and
they're ready to move forward, that's
when the ground lease is signed. The two
documents work together. Obviously, one
governs what happens prior to actually
signing the lease and then the lease
governs what happens for the next 99
years thereafter. Um I think most of the
salient points were in uh the legal
memo, confidential legal memo I provided
to you. Um but it's uh an asis say asis
transaction. Um there's no net cost to
the city. In other words, all costs of
operating the land are borne by partners
for environmental stewardship. Um there
are obligations that that were included
in the letter of intent that are
maintained in uh these documents uh that
require them to build the building in a
state of an art manner. Um and over the
18 months city staff has been convinced
that then in fact you will be very
pleased with what ends up happening. I
think their plans are to make this one
of the 35th building of its type in the
world. Not just the country but the
world. Um so very high aspirations for
this building. um and for its uses to
benefiting residents um uh directly
through programming. Uh there's multiple
reporting on the programming that's
required uh annually and then uh
programming plans need to be updated
every five years. Um so that there's a
constant communication with the city
staff and with city council uh through
the course of the 99-year lease as to
making sure that uh the program is
consistent with the preserve which the
city will be responsible for creating
and maintaining um that will be in and
around uh the 8 acres that the
environmental center sits on. Um based
on the legislative calendar, this matter
has been asked to be moved to council's
agenda for August 12th. Um, one of the
things I would suggest for you is that
if you have questions for me regarding
any of the specifics of the language in
these documents, it gives you plenty of
time to to get them and for us to get
answers back to you as well. Um, and I'm
happy to do so. Um, and again, we're
we're really pleased to be bringing this
to you this evening. at this point after
approximately 18 months of work um hard
work by by uh the High Foundation and
Partners for Environmental Stewardship
um they've already started their work in
anticipation of this going forward. Um
they've made that commitment even though
they don't have a signed deal yet. Um
and uh we're really excited about what
this is going to do for the city and
it's consistent obviously with the
comprehensive plan that was recently
adopted um and the previous resolution
that you um adopted uh in December.
Great.
Thank you. Um yeah, I uh very excited
about this project and to your point um
very much in alignment with uh the
comprehensive plan um and very excited
to hear about the standard of the build
as well as uh um just the level of
standard that's going to be exciting. So
um I do know we have uh members of the
high foundation and power partners of
environmental stewardship here. Um yeah,
they're here to observe this. Okay,
great. No presentation. Um, so, uh, with
that, any questions or comments from,
uh, the committee or full counsel?
Council Roy, Council President, Mr.
Hamburger, thank you so much for the
summary and for everyone's work on the
lease agreement. I know it's it's an
intense and long document. Um, and I
just wanted to say that I appreciate
that it has uh continued to capture the
um
the the pieces of the letter intent that
were originally included that were
originally improved by approved by
council um that were so important to us
in this in this particular agreement,
including the build standards, but also
the resident program uh resident
engagement and programming to benefit
the residents. And having that
continuous reporting in there is
incredibly important. And I think that
um I just wanted to say to council and
in general that I think that this is a
model for ways that we need to build
that into anything that happens in our
community because we can build that in
from the beginning and I feel like we've
done that here. So I feel really good
about that. So thank you.
Thank you council president. Any
additional questions or comments from
council?
Um my question is just around uh the
I guess I just want to make sure I
understand correctly what I read.
There's quite a lot of you know reading
to do. Um but in particular in the
agreements uh surrounding the water
line. Um
as I read it, it read as though that uh
Partners for Environmental Stewardship
would be required to
um allow for an easement for a water
line to go through the preserve. And I
guess is there any legal protection they
would have in regards to if
I guess we're talking about a preserve
and then building a water line through
it. Is there legal protection over over
the preserve piece of the property if
that makes sense? This my question makes
sense. So I mean keep in mind um the
water line would be something that the
city is proposing to build. Uh so it
would obviously have done the homework
to determine whether it would have any
damage to its property which is the
preserve. Um there are areas in the
peninsula that may need to ultimately be
served by water and we as a municipal
authority um regulated by the PUC very
well may have obligations to actually
provide water to them. Uh so we've left
open the options and abilities to run a
line um as long as it doesn't interfere
with um the environmental center itself.
Um and that's what they've agreed to
allow us to do. It goes across their
portion of the property. Whether that
came across the portions of the
preserve, there's no particular route
that's been determined yet. Obviously,
this is all about protecting the the
abilities in the future to maximize the
site for all, which is a part of what
the master site plan will help us do as
well. So, if I hear you correctly,
you're saying that it's in part to
protect the the possibility that the
city, you know,
if someone is seeking to tap into water
service that the city is able to run a
line where need be. Um, but then also
does provide the Partners for
Environmental Stewardship some
protection. Their building is absolutely
protected. Okay, that's correct. Okay.
Okay. And it was also helpful to hear
that there hasn't necessarily been a
particular route picked yet either.
Okay. Okay. I think that that answers my
question on that. Thank you. Very good.
Thank you, Councelor Hirs. Any
additional questions or comments?
Great. Uh my last question. Um just to
confirm, uh any motion to move this
forward would be for the August 12th uh
council meeting. Correct. Great. Thank
you. Um great. With that, uh, I will
motion to move administration resolution
number 50, 2025, uh, to the August 12th
council meeting. Second.
All those in favor? I. I. Great. Thank
you. Thank you.
Next, we'll move to resolution number
51, 2025, authorizing an amendment of
the official uh, sewage facilities plan
to include the Swan Hotel project.
Good evening. Good evening. I used to
turning around so many times. Good
evening. Uh Lauren Finn, senior planner
for the city. This um this sewer
planning module is for the Swan Hotel
redevelopment. So it's located at 101
South Queen Street. Um we've been
looking forward to the redevelopment of
of this um hotel for a while.
It's um an interesting piece in that it
actually doesn't have to go through a
full land development because they're
not changing so much to the um footprint
of the building. Um so they're just
going through kind of an abbreviated
process in land development and um the
process with the county as well for the
sewer module. Great.
Thank you. Thanks.
Any questions or comments from council?
any from the public.
Great. Uh with that, I'll motion to move
resolution number 51205
to the next full council meeting. So
move. All those in favor? I I. Great. Uh
council president, that concludes the
community planning committee. Thank you,
Council Royo. Uh next we have the public
works committee. Council Hirs. Thank
you, Council President. Um, we have two
items on the public works committee uh
meeting or agenda. The first of which is
resolution 52 um which is authorizing a
grant for the eastbound connector. Um
this is the
uh bicycle path that is going um towards
the go path east kind of in and around
um in and around Lincoln Middle School.
And the hope is to get that to
ultimately connect to the go path. I see
director Campbell coming up, so I'll let
him take over.
Thank you very much again for this
opportunity. This is um we're we're
submitting this a little bit early
because we're making a request for to
make this application to the multimodal
transportation fund. We had previously
made an application for si significantly
more money and were granted only
$200,000 which we now have. Um but
interestingly we've been invited to make
another application. Uh we do not yet
know what the what the likely amount is.
Part of the challenge with this
particular site is that it is three
municipalities. It is not only the city
of Lancaster but it is Manheim Township
and it's Lancaster Township. And
although we have a lot of participation
from um from both municipalities
um there each each municipality has a
varying level of of financial
capability. This is the opportunity to
to link pedestrian way a better
vehicular way and the active
transportation network from the burrows
the new burough school campus to the
Lancaster to the Macy campus as well.
Um, we have enough, we currently have
money in hand to do the design work and
to continue some of the the logistics of
working with the different
municipalities. Um, and some of some uh
lowhanging fruit work to be installed
before the end of 2027,
but the but we expect that the major
construction would be taking place as
late as 2031.
Um, if we are successful with this
application, which again we we're
hopefully coming back to you around for
the June 22nd as the first
opportunity to tell you what the cost is
because we're still awaiting guidance
from MTA MTF on how much they would
likely
be we would likely be eligible for. Um,
but that would allow us to reduce the
amount of money that's coming from our
from our 2025 bond at in the short term.
Uh, and that's money that could be used
for other purposes.
Thank you very much, uh, Director
Campbell. That's helpful. Um, yes, and
thank you for the explanation as well as
to why there's not an amount put there
yet. Um, appreciate that. um they're
willing to work with you on on that and
provide some guidance. Um so I will open
and to be clear this is this resolution
grants permission to apply for the
grant. Um so with that I will open up
comment to members of the public works
committee or full counsel.
Council Harsh. Thank you.
Um, I can't recall if uh it's the
resolutions accepting awards or if it's
the application that mentions if there's
a commitment or a match. Is there a
commitment or a match with these uh MTF
funds? Director Campbell, that's a very
good question.
Do you know?
We don't know, but we can make sure to
get that information to you. That would
be a question for the next meeting.
Thank you so much for for finding that.
I'm assuming that there is, but I don't
want to. I thought typically so. Okay.
Thank you, Council President. Uh,
councelor Clees. Oh, thank you,
Councelor Hush. Uh, Director Campbell,
uh, could you tell us uh, some of the
benefits of this project for the
community? Oh, yes. This is this is a
very interesting site because it is the
nexus of uh RankMill Road and um the uh
Walnut Street but also the um
what's the one that goes straight over
towards the operation center is RankMill
River? No. Pleasure or sorry Gratown
Gratown. We were going to hit it
eventually.
So there's a lot of students from all
three municipalities that traver that
will be traversing in this area because
of the extensive nature of the Lancaster
of the Mcaskky campus as well as the new
burough's elementary school which is
under construction right now. Um that
that particular roadway, Gratown Road in
particular, has excessive speeds right
now, partly because of people coming off
of off of uh Chestnut Street and flying
into that particular curve. There's
there's nothing that slows the traffic
in that particular area. This is an
opportunity for us to use our best
management practices that are that are
similar to what you've seen in other
parts of the city that we use for safe
streets for all and the vision zero
program to be able to reduce the speeds
in that particular stretch of the city
as well as to augment the active
transportation network. So this is one
of the key intersections where bike bike
lanes and bike access can be provided as
well. uh going up Broad Street. We as
you know there's the Chesapeake Broad
intersection that's that's under that
will be underway in 2026.
Um that provides a loop for people to
come from Southwest through Southeast up
to the Nasky campus, but also this is
this is one of the last connectors to
the the countywide active transportation
network which connects us to the goat
path among other things. So, we're very
much looking forward to the ultimate
design and resolution to be a much more
pedestrian friendly area with slower
speeds, slower traffic coming in this
particular area and controls. The a
couple of things that are being
considered are not just full
intersections, but also um stop lights,
possible intersection as well. Again,
we're that's still part of the study,
but what we need to make sure is that
students from the Buroughs community in
Lancaster Township can safely cross this
intersection and this series of streets
to the to the Masky campus and vice
versa. So, I think there's a lot of
benefits to this particular area. Thank
you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you, councelor H. Thank you,
council.
Got the answer to your questions. % So
70 70% and then so 7030 grand. Okay.
Thank you.
Are there any other questions or
comments from council?
Okay. Um hearing none, I will make a
motion to move this to our meeting of
council on July 22nd.
Second. All those in favor? I. Thank
you.
Um, and our next resolution is a
resolution recognizing uh Parks and
Recreation Month, resolution 53.
Forgive me, I'm pulling up the
resolution here. just to
um the resolution talks uh quite a bit
um about our partnership with the
Langster Direct Commission um and the
offering of of programming from our
parks um and recognizes you know the
great partnership that we've had with
them for decades um
and also recognizes the benefit that
parks uh have in our community. Um,
and thankfully, you know, we've been
putting a lot of effort into renovating
our parks. Um, so we recognize the value
that they provide to the city. Um, so,
you know, I won't read the resolution
out loud, but that's kind of some of the
things that it talks about. I know last
year we had um Heather Day from the
Lancaster Rec give a presentation. Don't
know if that's anything like that's
forthcoming this year, but um still do
think it's really important to recognize
uh both the value that the parks add to
our city, that the programming adds to
our city, um and then also all of the
all of the staff that makes that happen
um and all of the public works staff
that keeps our park clean. Um I'm really
grateful for them. So, um I don't really
have much else to say on this particular
resolution, but I want to make sure that
we recognize um all the people that work
hard to bring that benefit to our
community. So, I will open it up to uh
the public works committee or full
counsel if they have any comment.
Okay. Hearing none, um I will make a
motion to move this to our full meeting
of council on July 8th.
So move.
All those in favor? I
concludes. Yes.
I exerc exerciseed discretion and did
not feel it merited public comment at
this moment.
As a reminder, committee public comment
is not a requirement. Um,
that's all I really have to say on that.
Thank you, council. That concludes
public works committee. Appreciate it.
All right. Uh, counselors, we don't have
any committee of the whole items this
evening. The last item on our agenda is
the clerk's report. Mr. Harris
confirming that you've submitted that to
the council in writing. I have, Madam
President. Thank you very much. Then
reached the end of our agendas. I will
hear a motion to adjurnn. Motion to
adjourn. Second. Motion and a second.
All in favor? I. I. Thank you. We're
adjourned.